hello and welcome everyone it's January
16th
2025 we're in active inference guest
stream number 95.1 with riic Bry
discussing active inference for
self-organizing multi llm systems aasian
thermodynamic approach to adaptation so
riic thank you for joining looking
forward to your presentation and sharing
more And discussing so thank you to you
yep great thank you thank you Daniel for
having me um yeah so I'm going to talk
about kind of active inference for
self-organizing multi LM system so
basically making llm agents better with
active
inference so to motivate the problem a
little bit current multi LM agents kind
of have a lot of complex parameters for
example prompts um agent architecture um
tool use like these are things that you
can't just kind of fix what's parameter
optimization you have to find better
more intelligent ways to improve these
in time and that's not really a thing
right now um also another thing is that
llms themselves are used as a vector
adaptation for the agent in many ways so
for example in the Voyager paper um llms
are used to acquire new skills and then
use those skills to explore the
environment of Minecraft further um
which is which is useful but also quite
limited um and then the third thing is
that there's no formalized mechanis ISM
of balancing the exploration explo
exploitation tradeoff right now it's
kind of just using lm's internal
abilities to go about that but there's
no formalized mechanism and that kind of
limits a lot of the
potential now our solution is using
active inference to kind of overcome a
lot of these problems so the first thing
is that the best possible prompt for
different llms within the agent can be
learned over time these things are
something that we can figure out from
the environment we can Lear we can do
search to figure out what are the best
new prompting techniques so we can test
out different prompts to see which ones
give better scores on certain metrics so
these things can be learned over time
and the active inference
agent can help with that because now the
active inference agent becomes the
vector of adaptation allowing for real
learning through belief updates and
structural updates versus just solely in
context adaptation which is what llms
can do so we're actually learning and
actually adding information and updating
beliefs within our model and active
inference asks the formalized mechanism
to balance the explore exploit boundary
allowing for a more principled
understanding of uncertainty and also
giving us the option to verify
optimality see if the um see if the path
of selecting actions is actually an
optimal one or not which we can't do
with llms
directly so active inference works
through a generative model and um the
generative model we typically use for
active inference in discrete time is
called The partially observable Markov
decision process PDP now Mar Cod because
um current states are only influenced
directly by past States and it's
partially observable as opposed to a
regular mdp because of the agent doesn't
have the ability to directly observe the
States it must go through an observation
which allows it to update beliefs about
the states without any direct um direct
observation of the states So within
active inference we have several
matrices that we put into these um pdps
to encode the actual information that
we're learning from the environment or
that is contained within the environment
so the first thing is the a matrix or
the likelihood Matrix this is basically
just showing the relationships between
the likelihood um showing the
relationships between states and
observations so what are the chances
that this observation is related to this
state or the state produces this type of
observation the B Matrix is showing the
relationship between states at t+1 and
States at T time T so
basically what is the probability that
this state will occur at this time given
that this state occurred at a past time
now the C Matrix encod the preferences
at the Active inference agent so for
example if some of the states that this
model had was sunny weather and rainy
weather the C Matrix would encode that
the model like sunny weather and then
the D Matrix encodes the prior beliefs
Over
States now the ultimate goal is to
minimize surprise because surp low
surprise means that the model we have is
actually a good representation of its
environment but if we don't if we have
high surprise that means we're not
really understanding the environment
well because every observation we're
getting is surprising us so the goal is
to minimize surprise
and however the issue with just directly
minimizing surprise which is shown in
this equation here as negative log of
the probability overall
observations is that this is typically
intractable when the state space gets
really big and it it grows exponentially
so we can't directly minimize the um
surprise so we have to turn that into a
new quantity that we can more easily
approximate to instead of directly
Computing so this is how we derive
variational free energy by doing a a
variety of steps from base theorem to
get to this final
equation now the variation of free
energy equation is constituted of two
terms the complexity term and the
accuracy term so the complexity term is
basically just showing us the difference
between the distributions for the prior
beliefs and the posterior beliefs and
the accuracy term is just trying to show
us how close
um how well the observations that um how
well the states that we're um seeing and
how well those those observations align
with the states that we're seeing or the
states that we believe in so effectively
the goal is to minimize the difference
between our prior prior beliefs and
posterior beliefs and also to have our
absor our um beliefs be as accurate as
possible given the observations now the
way this actually happens is a um
minimization process like we said before
this is a a quantity want to approximate
to so this equation right here the DF
over dqs is just the partial derivative
of free energy in terms of the posterior
beliefs this is this first equation is
just showing the sh it in terms for one
state factor and when we do this we want
the um derivative to equal zero over
time but in practice what happens is the
max we have a max number of iterations
once those max number of iterations are
reached or the change in variational for
energy Falls below a certain threshold
the optimization process stops and we
have final posterior beliefs that have
minimized the quantities we want to
minimize this is the final posterior
belief equation shown right here
basically just showing
how the final posterior beliefs would
look how they're influenced by the prior
beliefs and how they're influenced by
the observations the current state
factor and also the other state
factors now the second quantity in um
active inference that we're trying to
minimize is the expected free energy now
this is related to policies and actions
and future States as opposed to
variational for energy which is very in
the
present so expected free energy is made
up of two terms um Information Gain and
uh pragmatic value so Information Gain
is just trying to show how much we
expect to gain by doing a certain action
so the way that transitions are
determined is they're conditioned on an
action so if we do this action what is
the likely outcome so right here we're
saying if we do this specific action so
a policy if we execute the certain
policy what is the likelihood of um
having significant Information Gain if
we have a lot of Information Gain that
means it's a um useful action because
it's highly informative and that's what
we want to optimize
for so the second term is called
pragmatic value also known as expected
utility this term is useful for
comparing the expected observations to
our preferred observations so as I said
before the C Matrix is the one that
encodes the preferred
observations and we want to since we
know since we have some idea of what the
expected states are in from the B Matrix
we also have some idea of what the
expected states are in the a matrix we
can figure out what the expected
observation should be as well and on
those expected observations we can do a
computation with the c Matrix to see how
high the expected utility or the
expected level of of referred
observations exists in the action we're
about to
commit the final part of um the final
part we need for this paper at least is
the a matrix updates so the a matrix is
the like I said before the Matrix that
encodes the relationship between states
and
observations but in our specific
implementation the agent doesn't
initially know exactly how the states
mapped observations it's intended to
learn that over time Time by getting in
new
observations so to do that we need to
have some mechanism to update it and
this is the mechanism so we do a similar
thing we did with variational free
energy where we take the derivative of
variational free energy with respect to
um the modality at or like the a matrix
with a certain modality and we basically
compute that over
time and then we take this equation and
then this equation turns into the final
derived equation below this final
derived equation below is just
explaining how we should update the a
matrix so the main updates are going to
come from the um outer product between
the observation and the current belief
so for example if you get an if you have
um two states that are um sunny and
rainy and the observation that you get
is that it's sunny all we would do is
update
the we would update the aspect of the
Sunny the the sunny part of the a matrix
to say that um
Sunny to say that we're getting an
observation that's sunny and then add
those to the counts of the a
matrix so getting to the actual specific
work done
um so this whole generative model
consists of three state factors so the
first is prompt combinations the second
is search States or Search terms and the
third is the info state
and then the seven observation
modalities so the accuracy relevance and
comprehensiveness observation modalities
are directly tied to the prompt States
the information relevance information
usefulness and Source quality modalities
so directly related to the search state
and then the info State just has three
modalities with an info State
observation modality and an infate State
Factor so they're directly related to
each other so that means any observation
and the infate modality is just a direct
reflection of the state
Factor so this just kind of shows this
figure just kind of shows the a matrices
for each of these State factors and
their relationship with the observation
modality so the first three is just for
the prompt quality
Matrix so this is basically just showing
the relationship between the three
quality matric we described the accuracy
relis and comprehensiveness and the
prompt States now initially you see all
these these um all these squares are
just blue this is because the model has
engaged in no learning it's starting
with a complete blank slate and has has
no understanding of the environment in
this specific
case now the way the generative process
actually works is that agents can select
actions so they can either select prompt
actions or search actions like we showed
before these are the two controllable
States now what a prompt action will do
is it'll take a certain set of prompts
that the agent selects it'll run them
through the actual research agent that
we're trying to optimize here it'll run
them through an agent it'll give certain
observations so as you can see this kind
of Json structure here what we're doing
is we're using a chat4 mini and that's
just going to give us a score from 0.0
to 1.0 counting up by 0.1 on the three
different metrics we need so for example
if an agent selects a prompt action we
first um run that prompt run those set
of prompts through the agent we get a
final result on that final result chat
T4 mini will evaluate it and then give
us three scores those three scores will
then get turned into an observation
vector and that observation Vector will
get passed back to the active inference
agent to use as observation now this is
the exact same process that happens for
the search action as well just with a
different prompt so this is actually the
prompt for the search action as you can
see we're telling the we're telling
trash to return scores on info relevance
usefulness and Source
quality now the info state is unique
because it's determined purely by the
amount of knowledge base so the way that
knowledge base works is by the amount as
search actions are um carried out and
more information is added to the
knowledge base um the info State goes
from no knowledge to some knowledge to a
high level knowledge and those are
observations that are directly getting
passed from the environment to the agent
so the agent doesn't actually have any
encoding of the information it's getting
from the search actions all it knows is
that there's some knowledge State coming
from the environment and it's using that
as a way to determine what to do next
and What observations uh it
prefers so yeah that's where that's
where that's where that's coming from
now for the
results um this is this is the same um
figure I should before but now with uh
learned um environment mappings so as
you can see for the first three matrices
these the prompts um the agent for each
prompt has a distribution over what
scores of expecting so for example for
the first prompt it's going for eight
and nine so it has a distribution saying
um it's most likely expecting so this is
the accuracy um this the accuracy metric
so it's saying that for prompt one for
prompt combination one it's generally
going to expect an eight or a nine on
the um accuracy metric and it does that
all the way through for all the prompts
and it does the same thing for search as
well so this is the um info relevance
metric so for example it's saying that
for prompt one it's generally going to
expect a score of nine out of 10 or 0.9
out of 1.0 on the um info relevance
metric so kind of all that and then the
info State metric is just concentrated
around um the second observation the
second observation is just High info so
like detailed information from the
environment this is because um the agent
was running over 20 trials and once and
the um info State metric gets to the
knowledge base that we have gets to a
high level pretty quickly and then so
that the info State kind of just keeps
getting observations about that it's in
a high level of information has high
level of information and just keeps
getting those observations so all
concentrated around that observation
specifically now one of the main points
of this was to show how we could um show
how we could go through the explore
exploit tradeoff really well by using
active inference and this is kind of
showing that so this is some time series
data from time Step Zero all the way to
time step 80 um the red dots are search
actions and the blue dots are prompt
actions so as you can see we have a
preponderance of search actions in the
initial stages because the agent is
trying to learn the environment um
trying to get more information and stuff
like that so it's trying to kind of
understand how prompts work how prompt
prompting works and then at the towards
the end is there's mainly search actions
or sorry mainly prompt actions as the
agent is testing these prompts to see if
they work well or if they work don't
work well kind of using the information
it's gotten from the search actions now
we we know it's not actually using this
this is more kind of a simulation but um
it's using it in the sense that it knows
that we already have a lot of
information from the environment because
of that info State observation it's
getting so in conclusion what we what we
did here was that we had the model
effectively learned the environment's
generative process mapping the hidden
mapping the observations to the hidden
States um we were able to simulate
humanlike exploratory behaviors with
active searching and testing multiple
possibilities and then the main thing is
that we were able to enhance the
capability of llms as well as enhanced
capability of active inference because
we gave llms a formalized structure that
they didn't have before to execute um uh
learning through and we gave active
inference the ability to operate in
high-dimensional Spaces by integrating
llms with if we had to try to encode
this functionality directly into the
active inference agent it would have
been much more harder and much more
complex than just having the llm
Outsource everything to the llm and have
it do a lot of the work so we kind of
had um improvements on both ends through
the
system I just want to talk about
some some uh future directions for this
so obviously the one big thing that this
model doesn't have is encoding actual
Knowledge from the environment so as we
perform search actions we're getting
information about promps right so we're
saying so if we look up if we look up um
what are the best ways to prompt for
chbt it'll say like tree of thought
Chain of Thought blah blah blah etc etc
but none of this information is actually
getting encoded into the agent all all
that's happening is that there's an info
state right and it's using that info
state to determine his future actions
but it would be much more useful if the
active inference agent actually knew why
search certain prompts or certain um
prompt combinations were good based on a
search actions and then use that
information directly to influence his
actions so making that that would
require some sort of hierarchical model
and making that would be a good feature
direction for this um another thing is
giving the ability the giving the agent
the ability to dynamically expand its
state space to not be constrained to a
fixed set of prompts so here what we did
was we just had a fixed set of prompts
for prompts for each uh part of the
agent and and obviously like there's
much more the space of possible prompts
is Infinite Space and there's there's a
lot more we could explore if we weren't
constrained by a fixed State space so
expanding on that would be very useful
and also the third thing would be to
equip the agent with the ability to
modify other complex parameters such as
instead of just prompts maybe also be
able to modify the architecture of the
agent or the tools it's using and stuff
like that the evental goal is to make a
general kind of agent brain that has the
capability to plug be plugged into any
llm agent and exhibit human levels of
learning uh modification structure
learning and stuff like
that
um so
yeah I think that's
it awesome thank you for the
presentation for those watching live
they can write questions while I'm just
cropping and getting everything back
maybe uh share a little bit how did you
come to this project where are you at in
your education and and research and all
of
this yeah sure so yeah my well I only
found out about active
inference maybe a year ago and kind of
how I happened upon it is that um I
wanted to kind of do this general idea
that I just said like the agent brain so
because I noticed that llms were pretty
static and or like llm agents were
pretty static and then humans had to
directly go in and like oh let me fix
this prompt or let me let me change the
order of these two nodes and stuff like
that and this seemed kind of you know
lm's LM themselves can do a lot of that
improvement work but it seemed like
there was a big hole there that we could
just fill by having some sort of
self-organizing behavior um and that's
kind of how I happened upon active
inference because it was just like
modelbased so
we were like responsible for um figuring
out how to like actually structure the
um J of model and the J of process that
the agent was going to work with and um
it was very sample efficient which I
really liked because there's generally
you don't get that many samples in a
typical workload so for example if we're
using an agent in production we wouldn't
really be getting unless it was being
used at massive scale we wouldn't be
getting too many examples that we could
work with to improve certain functions
and the sample efficiency of active
inference really kind of helps with that
um issue and then the other thing was
the reinforcement learning obviously
just having some aspect of being able to
learn over time with llms you can't
really do that it's all in context and
I'm suspicious that in context learning
is or just having information in context
is enough to replicate the abilities
that a reinforcement learning scheme can
provide so that's kind of how I happened
upon this and started looking into it I
actually read the um
Thomas par Carl friston
textbook um on this and that's kind of
how I got into it started doing some
work and yeah kind of came to
this cool okay I'm gonna read some
questions from Arun nuran a colag at The
Institute and then any other questions
in live chat we'll we'll see okay so
thanks thanks Arun for the awesome
submitted questions all right what does
it mean to ask an llm for a numerical
score of something can we really convert
the sampling of the next token's
probability distribution of an llm into
a meaningful quantitative
observation
so it's it's kind of a um the llm
observation is kind of a uh a pro maybe
approximation or like
uh kind of a
maybe an easy easy way to do this
basically so all we're doing is we're
saying like because the best the best
text readers at this time in AI or text
um understanding machines kind of are
llms because the way this whole the way
this is working is that the LMS are
getting just a bunch of text because the
the research agent is outputting a bunch
of text and the active inference agent
directly can't really do much with this
because language is a hard space to to
understand and active inference would
need a lot more improvements to be able
to understand that space so basically
what we're doing is that we're kind of
simplifying the complex dat space of
just the English language and we're
simplifying it into something the active
inference agent can understand so what
we're doing is that the llm can
understand language and it can kind of
generate certain scores obviously the
llm scores aren't as useful or nuanced
as a human scoring certain like text
would be so for example if there's an
competition an llm would probably be a
much worse scorer for this for those
essays in a consistent manner than a
human would be because it's kind of hard
to determine what the standards are but
for something like this where the text
is relatively simple um it's pretty easy
for the llm to just say this is the
score I'm giving to the text we give it
certain like guidelines to follow when
assigning scores so it just gives a
certain score and that score is kind of
a
basically a simplification of the state
space of all possible language into just
three values that we can use to kind of
help the help the active inference agent
learn now ideally it would just be the
active inference agent directly
digesting the language but this is kind
of an easy way to overcome that um
massive Gap in complexity yeah great
response all out a few
comments you pointed right there that a
longer term research agenda is like an
active inference Linguistics model using
some kind of syntax and semantics on the
natural language itself and so some kind
of you know Mega hierarchical model or
something cool like that but in in in
the
meanwhile for specific purposes we can
take natural language expressions use
llms especially with the Json or
structured output and project them onto
numerical lower dimensional State spaces
like how many bird species are mentioned
in this paragraph only respond with a
specific number three and then you have
an a matrix that takes in as an
observation the number of bird species
observed and then maps to some other
variable for the ecosystem or how many
facts in this paragraph correspond to
this circumstance and so then the active
inference generative model can pick
up at the interface of the output of the
structured llm return so it's it's a
design pattern I think that's very
rapidly emerging and it's exciting to
see that that you're working on it
because it really does bring together
this Mega parametric you know Millions
to billions of parameters High
dimensional State spaces more generic
architectures for llm and such and then
take the output sometimes crystallized
down to just like a single scalar value
or to a vector of numerical values pick
up there with the more interpretable
smaller and Sample efficiency and direct
belief updating and then just one more
piece I'll say there is you can get an
llm to give a quantitative or natural
linguistic representation of its own
uncertainty but then there's this kind
of head scratching moment where it's
like well even if it says that it's 55%
confident that is the most
likely chain of tokens for it to say
it's not a true introspection of its
actual
uncertainty and so again further down
the road that's a promising Avenue for
active inference models that can
introspect and accurately have their own
uncertainties however in the meanwhile
this is one way that we can make the
best of what exists today and what we
can build
tomorrow exactly and one other thing
I'll add is that some kind of what I'm
trying to do as well
is llms can already do a lot so kind of
have llms do as much as possible but
also try to kind of like what I was
saying before like having the acttion
inform be able to encode the information
itself from the environment like add
things to the active information over
time and then offset some of the
responsibility of the llm so that we're
getting the actual interpretability on
like proper uncertainty estimation and
all that stuff within the active
inference agent without having to rely
on the llm but we kind of can like
basically like if active insurance is
here and the LM is doing all this we can
kind of just like you know move that Gap
over time as we develop more but we're
still getting the performance to start
with you know that that's kind of funny
makes me think of like a Grass Is Always
Greener um or or some kind of complement
where for the
llms we might gain interpretability by
projecting down to smaller State spased
models that have real quantitative
variance estimators whereas as for
active inference models we can gain
interpretability and accessibility by
translating them out to natural language
so you know yeah yeah that's a great way
to put it yeah more tools better okay
aroon asks next
question over what time scales did your
active inference plus llm agent execute
how did that change with the complexity
of the questions
asked H well what was the time the
runtime Dynamics like how how long does
one full loop
take yeah I mean it's pretty short so it
was 20 it was it was about like 80 80
times steps so kind of just 80 like 20
trials four time steps for trial um the
time steps only were relevant to the
info State um the info state or
information State because the other two
didn't really have any transition
Dynamics but effectively yeah what it
would just be is that for each time step
there would be some sort of action the
llm would run through all the stuff it
had to run through for the agent so the
research agent would run that we're
trying to optimize and then the
evaluation on that result would run and
then we would have that observation we'
put it back into the acence model so
that would be one full-time step so that
maybe took like in terms of actual time
to run the research agent run the
evaluation and then the active in model
itself
maybe each time step took like 10
seconds um it was relatively quick
especially because we're using like 40
mini which is like faster than something
like 40 maybe um and the active agent
was like the state space was pretty
small so it didn't take much time for
the AC agent to run as well so yeah cool
yeah I could see the latency of the llm
being a major determinant whether you
use kind of a smaller or a faster
or whether you do something that that
takes a bit to get chugging okay cool
all right arun's next question did you
actually get good answers to research
questions you
asked um well the uh the uh llm itself
already worked so or the research agine
itself already worked so like they it
had certain prompts and um it would
output something so for example if I ask
like what give me give me like a report
on coffee or something it'll go through
the entire you know it was basically
five aspects to the research agent it
was um planning reviewing uh actually
like or getting information from the
internet answering the question and if
there's like uh any issues with the
answer then it would route back to the
initial planning stage and then kind of
go back from there so the asent itself
was already like relatively good at
giving answers um giving good answers or
giving good reports on whatever question
you asked mainly the point of this was
just to show that because like if you
think about it in time like the prompts
will become like worse and worse over
time because prompting techniques get
better well they'll get worse and worse
in the sense that like we our knowledge
of how to prompt increases for example
like we initially used to only think
about like oh like step-by-step
prompting that was like the max of what
prompting could
now we have like so many different
techniques like you have like tree of
thought Chain of Thought a react
framework blah blah blah there's like so
many different techniques and if we had
started in like 2023 with just the um
step-by-step prompting and we as a human
didn't go back in there and fix it
ourselves then we would just be stuck
with those bad prompts compared to where
the literature is at right now so the
idea was that right well for this was a
fixed State space with just like it was
like five prompts for agent that we that
we had to work with and then those would
be formulated into com combinations of
prompts that the active INF agent could
select so it's just kind of a like a
simple way to show that like the active
inference agent could pick these prompts
pick the best one um research from the
environment and then kind of do this
whole process to try to learn like which
is the best prompt in that very small
state space over time so it wasn't like
it's not going to change the
effectiveness of the research agent too
much because the state space of the
prompts is so small but I mean it was
already good to begin with and it was
good to end
with yeah thanks a few comments on that
we're seeing at this moment just such an
exponential increase in the capacity so
as you point out even 6 months or a year
can be very different and it's an
exciting time for understanding research
and cognitive science agents overall
like I think think about the graph
structured knowledge bases like bu's uh
graph preflex type models where where
you know limitations of in context
learning that you pointed to can be
addressed with some operations on
knowledge graphs and it's like we're
kind of exploring
motifs and initial pattern designs
improves the concepts for how these
kinds of synthetic intelligence systems
and augmented systems with human and
non-human entities can be collaborating
in information spaces epistemically and
like everything from the user interface
and and the the accessibility and the
human computer side on through what are
we really yielding are we synthesizing
new molecules are these revealing errors
in previous derivations in papers or
these you know shorter algorithms like
so it's just like wow happy 2025 huh
right um how Arun asked how did this
compare to purely llm driven agents for
example llm plus while loop Plus tool
calling yeah
so using
llms um we can definitely use like LMS
directly to improve the agents so kind
of just say like so we have this
research agent we just have the LM go in
and
say um like if every time like every
like let's say like every day do
research on like all these topics around
prompting um synthesize that research
put it in your context and then use that
context to like look at all these five
prompts make them better now if we just
said that the llm is going to do way
better than the active inflence model
right now because obviously llm can
explore an infinite States Bas on
language and we only have like five
prompts we're looking at and we can't
really like we right now there's no
actual thing where like the search doing
the search is actually changing the
prompts or changing the U prompt
selection mechanism or anything like
that so yeah LM by itself would perform
way better than the model currently this
is more
like but the issue is that like at the
end of the day it's all in context
learning with LL and there's no way to
maintain like a real understanding of
the environment over time like actually
encoded within belief updates and these
matrices and that's what the active
inference is bringing and this is more
kind of like a proof of concept to show
that like we could do that at some point
because let just thinking about it
theoretically a easy way to improve this
is just to say kind of like how I said
like the llm can just take in context
blah blah blah now we we could just do
something simpler where we could say now
the llm go do this research every day
take and that put it in your context now
turn that into um states that we can or
state factors that we can put within the
active inference agent now the active
inance agent has a whole new set of
State factors or and States within those
factors and now I can use that directly
to um learn about new prompting
techniques and it has new like it's
Dynam State space is dynamically going
to change because that is adding new
prompts all the time and this way like
it's a much better way of having the
active INF stent actually learn these
prompts and it's probably I mean we
don't know yet but most likely it's
going to perform better than the llm
just doing it in in context by itself
but it's like a pretty simple way
because of just like having the LM do a
lot of the work because without that the
active inference agent like the same
kind of process I described just purely
with an active inference would take a
really long time to figure
out yeah that that reminds me of how
many ways we're seeing pop up
that computer science and AI is sort of
rediscovering or Reinventing cognitive
science like knowing that versus knowing
how knowing where to look to get more
information and then it's like okay well
let's just say we are going to have our
um grad student I mean research agent
and they're going to be doing some daily
task we say well I want the report to be
balancing accuracy and complexity well
that's variational free energy or right
in terms of prospective experimental
design what should be the Criterion well
the reinforcement strategy is with some
sort of large or curated or labeled
database train an auxiliary reward
function and then just go ahead and try
to hill climb on that reward function
well what if we're into the unknown
we're on the frontier we don't
necessarily have a training data set um
or maybe we we wouldn't even want one
even if we could so then what criteria
should we use that's directly based on
the model that yields pragmatic and
epistemic value and the expected free
energy this explicit explore exploit
tradeoff and and the ability to modulate
between returning expected results with
a high expected utility to learning and
then it's like just like you gave that
kind of daily duty cycle with like every
day go and research something and then
that could be encoded kind of during
sleep leap into beliefs like what is the
the 0 to1 and a variance on what is the
likelihood that this is going to happen
or what's the efficacy of this treatment
over that treatment and then that gives
an actual Information Gain term so that
it doesn't just continue to do the same
internet searches again and again rather
those searches are tuned for epistemic
Value so it's like and then to the Chain
of Thought and tree of thought well this
is where we get into questions like
rumination where you could have at a
hyper parametric level you could think
too little and leave good thoughts kind
of unthought on the table so to speak or
you could ruminate and you could think
too long and be past the point of
diminishing return well where is the
parto optimal point for how long you
should be thinking that's a
metacognition question that's a
cognitive security question and so it's
like it's really interesting to see even
though they've been coming from the
Horizon with these Mega parametric
models they're actually converging to
some of the formalisms and the
tradeoffs that cognitive science has
been working with for a long time
related to everything from like
epistemic foraging and memory and skill
to metacognition so I mean so cool how
it's all coming together right I think
like Google even recently was focusing
one of their models on surprise so they
were using surprise as the reward
function to kind of improve their models
and it's kind of like that's I mean
that's Act of inference right there so
it's kind of it is kind of cool that
we're seeing these Concepts in active
inference kind of extend out to um just
like llms and diffusion models and stuff
like that yeah and and although
minimizing surprise is maximizing model
evidence
there isn't a tractable heris to
bound success or evidence whereas there
is one to bound
surprise again even though they're kind
of duel so there's an interesting right
relationship there okay next Arun
question why does the a matrix need a
specific action dependence I believe
pmdp should create a b control state for
every action anyway so you should be
able to set those out of the box as it
were well the a the a matrix doesn't
have any action dependence it's just the
the actions are able to provide
observations that the a matrix can use
to update itself but the a matrix itself
doesn't have any like action dependence
it is all through the B Matrix so the
one thing is that like the B like the
prompt and um search states are
controllable but they don't have any
real like any like legitimate transition
Dynamic so like just because like if we
commit some sort of action it's not
actually causing the um prompt
combination at one state to transition
to The Prompt combination at another
state it's more that we are picking
those prompt combinations
independently or independently in the
sense that like this basically just
going to be deriving from expected free
energy so whichever is the lowest
expected free energy is one the one
we're pick
but there's no like the action isn't
directly causing the transition
from prompt combination one to prompt
combination two the only thing where
that's actually happening is the info
state so like I I think in the code or
in the code there's um like B Matrix
learning as well but it really only
happens for the um info State the other
the B matrices for the prompt States and
the search states are completely this
the same over time kind of just showing
that like they really don't have any
direct this action causes this state to
this state kind of you know Dynamics
there cool um thanks for clarifying and
this is sort of a classic
design degree of Freedom or or openness
for for those who have explored these
cognitive models which is what exactly
should the agents know about the
consequences of its action because if it
doesn't know the consequences of action
it just going to be flailing wildly
whereas if it's given too much
information about the consequences of
action it's kind of like putting the Cat
in the Hat because it's going to know
exactly what it's going to do so that's
where having the B Matrix learning and
having these learning methods is really
cool and really helpful because then you
can see okay how with what learning rate
and what kind of variability in action
and in the generative process in the
niche what what Dynamics yield
over what time scales the convergence to
veridical learning of the consequences
of action so maybe it needs to spin
10,000 prompts out before it understands
the consequences of certain kinds of
prompting maybe it only needs to throw
out a few depending on what it is so
okay and then one more question from
Arun and then if anyone in the live chat
has questions they can write it he wrote
similar question to R Bellamy another
Discord colleague how did you find using
lra L graph it seems like quite a
polarizing framework but still probably
easier to use than PDP sweating
Emoji uh yeah definitely it's easier to
use than pmdp I have to do a lot of uh
like going into pmdp and changing like a
lot of the like source code kind of to
like make all of this work which was
useful for me but it was uh
but yeah Lang graph um actually I um
I've run a company where we build AI
agents for other clients and companies
like that and we typically use l graph
for everything so it wasn't too hard
because I'm kind of I have a lot of
experience in that but
um yeah but the pp was definitely harder
that's for sure what what what
functionality does the link graph
provide like how does it and how does it
interface or pass to
imdp yeah so um The Lang graph is
basically just a framework to kind of uh
create nodes and edges and the main
other thing is that it can save State
between like agent runs so you can
Define nodes and for each node for this
Lang graph agent for example each node
was a llm that executed a certain action
so it would be like either it was
answering the question or it was doing
research or it was planning or something
like that and each node would do certain
things um Lang graph allows you to like
kind of Simply Define controlled edges
between those nodes so you can say this
node directly needs to this node um but
if some if this happens then it should
lead to this node just kind of
conditional edges and um it also allows
you to save State So within as the agent
is running you can kind of save uh just
save like each the result at each uh
stage so like if this node R ran like it
saved the list if this node run is saved
in the list and that kind of allows you
to call back to use this information
from this past node to inform your
answer for this spe this specific node
and kind of just it's just like a simple
framework to kind of allow you to just
build um agents
effectively um I don't really yeah I
think I think it is hard if you don't
have like a good framework to go off of
but we've kind of like built a framework
over time and actually the agent that's
used in the um the the code I put out is
uh is using that framework so if you
might find that helpful if you want to
build some L graph
agents yeah where do you see it all sort
of going with different agentic
Ai
and where where would it look more like
a fusion agents or or collaborative
swarms or mesh like what do you think we
might see
yeah I think I'm a big proponent of the
idea that we're going to have like
billions of AI agents just kind of all
talking to each other like basically
just like a whole AI population like we
have a human population I think that's
probably very likely to happen
because at the end of the day like
there's probably gonna I'm skeptical
that one model is going to be able to
vastly overpower humans to the extent
that like a bunch of models will be able
to so like as you can see in like the
typical like llm Literature Like if you
combine for example like if you're in
your reasoning Cycles combine Claude um
chat BT um llama and like if you combine
those together in your reasoning it
typically performs better than if you
just use only chat BT in Loops or only
claw in Loops so kind of having
different models trained in the slightly
different ways is probably going to help
increase performance by a significant
amount so I think we're going to
probably have a lot like billions of
Agents just communicating with with each
other maybe at the speed of light
because it's all just information and
they don't have to communicate in
language like we do as
humans but um yeah I kind of see that
going there and then at least in the
near future I think we're like kind of
what we were saying um we're probably
going to see a big rise in using these
kind of formalized Frameworks to improve
agents so like active inference or
there's all like a lot of there's other
basian reinforcement learning schemes
there's typical reinforcement learning
schemes um those stuff are already being
used but I think there probably going to
be a big rise in that as the um as the
kind of benefits from just purely using
like llm reasoning kind of taper off I
think we're going to see a big rise in
that as
well that's very interesting like going
back to the sort of grass greener we
could see a situation where smaller
interpretable active inference type
models are using high-dimensional
interfaces like natural language sharing
information and the opposite setting
where
large sort of opaque models are
communicating through well structured
narrow
channels that are active inference like
State
spaces and just sending each other that
Jon
kind of like as a semantically encrypted
communication you know right it just say
31 two and it's just like oh
no that's actually a really ins
insightful Point yeah it might just be
that all these LMS are communicating
through yeah these narrow kind it's kind
of like how we communicate too it's not
like I can't just directly pass my
thoughts to you you know like ideally if
I could like you would get a lot more
information about what I'm thinking like
what I'm feeling stuff like that we have
to communicate through Words which is
kind of a narrow representation of what
our thoughts actually are so maybe LMS
have like a similar you
know lot to say about that but that
again comes to the cognitive science
topics of of
communication semantics theory of Minds
you know how cool
right cool exactly um yeah what are your
next next moves with your education and
everything and then if there's anything
else you want to add you can go for
it just continue to do um continue to do
this research try to expand um right now
actually what I'm working on is the
thing I said about like actually
encoding knowledge within the agents
instead of just using some like like um
unknown kind of info State modality I'm
working on that right now um kind of
using a hierarchical model
um so I think that's like the near
future kind of yeah I just want to
continue working on this whole idea of
like combining active inference and llms
to do as like much interesting things as
possible and improve llms and active
inference at the same time um one other
thing is actually I thought was really
interesting um was I was reading the
paper on uh renormalizing gen of models
from uh car and all of them but I think
that that seems really interesting
because obviously one of the big
problems with active inference is just
scale it's it's kind of hard to just
keep making more and more and more
complex models over and over again like
like llms and like typical reinforcement
learning have it easy because they just
put a policy on it and just like put a
bunch of data in there and then they're
good to go you know but we actually have
to like painstakingly like build all
these sh of models and it kind of slows
our progress down a lot so using these
reing gen models um to kind of just take
take away that whole scale problem it
can just kind of run these group
Transformations on
any any space of any scale um would be
pretty useful I'm trying to explore see
how I could use that as well I think one
interesting thing with that is doing it
doing the rgm transformation in more
like abstract State spaces so like in
the paper they use stuff like um like
pixels and stuff like that like physical
spatial spaces right but maybe doing it
some on something like language
might be a little harder because how
exactly do you like there's no there's
no like exactly pixel equivalent of
language you know because pixels are
simple you could just say this is a
discrete quantity the only way you can
differentiate this discrete quantities
is by RGB values and you're like good to
go but with language it's kind of like
you
have each it's not like each letter
really means anything and putting
letters together has different meaning
and putting saying words together has
different meaning so it's kind of a hard
it's a much harder problem to solve to
use the G like renormalizing of models
on these language spaces versus just
spatial spaces so I think that's also an
interesting problem but yeah kind just
trying to think about these things see
what contributions I can make yeah cool
yeah great comments from earlier par
anden at all work on reading as
multiscale active inference there's the
icade it's reducing uncertainty on the
letter then right letter to letter to
reduce uncertainty on the word and then
they go up to the third level with a
narrative you know cat at bird or was it
the bird ate the cat so those kinds of
things you got prior over letters
transition matrices all these uh kinds
of things um and then but that was as
you put it painstakingly crafted and
where could we abstract and have
generalized
templates so that perhaps an adapter
module is crafted to connect a given
domain or system of interest to some
known interoperable scheme and then
something like an rgm can take over from
there um okay I'm I'm gonna ask one more
one more question from the chat and then
that'll be great okay all right um are
you using meta learning aspects in the
system to enable self-guided research
and are
Direction opinions guided simply by
ACM or what was that last part or
Direction
opinions guided simply by
actim okay
um yeah there's really no meta learning
the learning rate is stable throughout
the entire thing um
yeah the direction opinions are are like
in which like which search action should
be taken or should it should a search
action be taken and should a prompt
actually be taking that's all purely
Guided by active inference yeah so that
was kind of the main point was that the
active inference has this formalized
structure that can allow for like
optimality in terms of like exploration
exploitation so the active inference
agent is purely responsible for picking
the actions and um determining where to
go next yeah epic well thank you very
much for joining I hope
you engage and and find uh collaborators
and replicators who are interested in
this hot topic of active inference and
llms and come back when you're ready for
95.2 all right cool okay thank you thank
you peace bye